<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An Humble request to Protestants to promote religion and trade with directions how to do it.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 40KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 11 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A45105</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12895686</idno>
  <idno type="VID">95175</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240896819</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing H3646</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R4445</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">12895686</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A45105)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 95175)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 919:29)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An Humble request to Protestants to promote religion and trade with directions how to do it.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[3], 16 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Samuel Crouch ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1688.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Bristol Public Library, Bristol, England.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="topical_term">Christian life.</term>
               <term type="geographic_name">Great Britain --  Commerce.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-05 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-08 </date>
            <label>Zev Berger </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-08 </date>
            <label>Zev Berger</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:95175:1"/>
            <p>An Humble REQUEST TO PROTESTANTS, To Promote RELIGION and TRADE; WITH DIRECTIONS how to do it.</p>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Psal. 112.9.</hi>
                  </bibl> He hath dispersed, he hath given to the poor; his righeousness endureth for ever: his horn shall be exalted in honour.</p>
               <p>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Prov. 11.30.</hi>
                  </bibl> He that winneth souls, is wise.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>Samuel Crouch,</hi> at the Corner of <hi>Popes-head-Alley</hi> in <hi>Cornhill.</hi> 1688.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="colophon">
            <pb facs="tcp:95175:2"/>
            <p>This may be Printed.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <date>
                     <hi>April</hi> 3. 1688.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>ROB. MIDGLEY.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:95175:3"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:95175:3"/>
            <head>An Humble REQUEST TO PROTESTANTS, To Promote RELIGION and TRADE, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>'TIS no small unhappiness that the Christian World is so much deform'd and weaken'd by its un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charitable (and therefore unchristian) divisions and animosities, most men being more hot for the sentiments of their own Party, than for the common Principles of Christianity wherein we are all agreed; and bestowing that Zeal upon the former, which is due only to the latter; which sad consideration would put a stop to this truly Christian proposal, did I not hope, that some (tho I fear but few) had rather bestow their time and labour upon such a Paper as this, than on the useless (or worse) Pam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phlets wherewith our age abounds: The poor and low de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>signs of which, do make wise men suspect almost every thing they read; therefore I do (to obviate such Objections) as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure you, that I shall (by God's assistance) as fully practice the following directions, as I desire my Reader should.</p>
            <p>My humble Request is this, That you would, according to your several abilities, as good Stewards of the manifold Blessings of God, contribute to the necessities of the Church and Poor, for the Glory of God, and the Good of the Souls
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:95175:4"/> and Bodies of those, whose sad conditions call for your speedy help.</p>
            <p>That I may promote so good a work, I shall</p>
            <p n="1">1. Lay before you some Considerations to perswade you hereunto.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Present you with some fit objects of your Charity, or direct you where to bestow it.</p>
            <p>I shall be very brief in the first of these, because the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verend Dr. <hi>Barrow,</hi> in his Sermon of <hi>The Duty and Reward of Bounty to the Poor,</hi> hath handled this Subject very fully, which I desire you seriously to peruse; and only at present consider,</p>
            <p n="1">1. That your selves, and all you have, are God's, and must be used accordingly. No created being can call him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self, or any thing he possesseth, his own, by original and absolute propriety: For as God is the first Cause, so is he the last end of all his creatures. <hi>Of him, and through him, and (therefore) to him are all things,</hi> Rom. 11.36. 'Tis true, the worst of men have, under God, a right to their Estates. God gave to <hi>Jehu</hi> and his Sons for four Generations a right to the Throne of <hi>Israel,</hi> 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 10.30. and to assert the contrary, <hi>viz.</hi> That wicked men are Usurpers of all they enjoy, is destructive of Justice and Charity, and would be to dissolve all Civil Societies, and turn the World into a Chaos: But yet you must remember, that you are Stewards, not Lords of all you have; you must not therefore dispose of your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster's Goods at your own pleasure, but use them according to his directions. To do otherwise, is to be guilty of Atheism, Idolatry, and Injustice, by denying the Soveraign Lord of the World, and worshipping that grand Idol sinful-self; by robbing God of what is his by right of Creation and Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, and bestowing it upon his greatest Enemies. O! that you had the same apprehensions of these things now, which you will have when you must give account of your Steward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship, of all the talents your Lord hath committed to your trust! Pray bear with my plainness; Do you believe there will be a day of reckoning, or no? If not, do Christianity the right to renounce it; but if you believe, as you profess to do, I humbly beg that you would take care that your
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:95175:4"/> Faith be not dead. Think it not enough, with those here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical and pretended Christians St. <hi>James</hi> speaks of, to say, <hi>Depart in peace, be ye warmed, be ye fill'd,</hi> James 2.16. but practice that Religion he describes, <hi>ch.</hi> 1.27. <hi>Pure Religion and undefiled before God and the Father, is this, to visit the father<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>less and widow in their affliction,</hi> lest you be the persons to whom he speaketh, Chap. 5.1, 2, 3. <hi>Go to now ye rich men, weep and howl, for your miseries which shall come upon you,</hi> &amp;c. Had I not found such expressions in the Word of God, I durst hardly have presum'd to write them. I pray there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore look on them as the Word of that God who is no re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>specter of persons; before whom, ere long, rich and poor must stand on even ground.</p>
            <p>This first consideration will not only discover your indispen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sable obligation to, but also be of very great use to direct what proportion of your Estates ought to be employed in acts of Charity: For it affords this general rule, That you must bestow so much of your Estates upon your selves and Families, as may fit you to do the work of your Soveraign Lord in your respective places; and employ the rest for the good of the Souls and Bodies of your fellow-subjects. You have all from God, and must use all for him. <hi>Whether ye eat or drink, or whatever ye do, do all to the glory of God.</hi> The knowledg of the End, will mightily direct you how to use the Means. But alas! How few are guided by this Rule in our degenerate Age? O that I could perswade you as faithful Stewards, to take a strict account how you dispose of your Master's Goods; and then let Conscience, directed by your Lord's Will and Commands, tell you, whether so much spent in delicious fare, was to please an inordinate appetite, or to fit you for your Duty; whether so much laid out for fine Cloaths, rich Furniture, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> nay, so much laid up for Childrens Portions, might not (at least a considerable part of it) have been employed more to the Glory of God, had it been disposed of according to the following Directions? Think before you speak, when you say you have nothing for charitable uses; This concerns not only those who have Thousands or Hundreds <hi>per Annum,</hi> but men of meaner for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes: those that labour for their livelihood not accepted,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:95175:5"/> Ephes. 4.28. <hi>Let him that stole, steal no more; but rather let him labour, working with his own hands that thing that is good, that he may have to give to him that needeth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Pray consider what God hath done for you, and you will find, that not only Justice, but Love and Gratitude oblige you to this Duty. He hath given you Souls which by his Grace are capable of Eternal happiness; and Bodies fit for those Souls to act in: And (which is more than your very beings) he hath given his Son to be a propitiation for your sins. What hath God done for you in making you Men and Christians? And I hope you look upon those Riches and Honours you so much value, to be the Gifts of God. And can you once imagine, that he hath given you more wages than others, that you may do less work? Our Lord, who spake as never Man did, affirms the contrary, Luke 12.48. <hi>For unto whomsoever much is given, of him shall be much re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired; and to whom men have committed much, of him will they ask the more.</hi> The consideration of God's Infinite good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness in himself, and his unspeakable bounty to you, should inflame your hearts with love to him. A Love, not in word only, but in deed and truth; a love that expresseth it self by obedience to all his Commands, particularly that of loving your Neighbours as your selves: without which, the most splendid profession of Religion, and highest pretentions to Devotion, will not argue your love to God. 1 John 4.10. <hi>He that loveth not his brother whom he hath seen, how can he love God whom he hath not seen?</hi> 1 John 3.17. <hi>But whoso hath this worlds goods, and seeth his brother have need, and shutteth his bowels of compassion from him, how dwelleth the love of God in him?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. As your obligations to this duty are many and great, so the rewards assign'd to it are unspeakable, both in this World and that which is to come. The present pleasure of doing good, is it self a great reward; but very inconsiderable, if compar'd to that now promised, but to be enjoyed hereafter. <hi>Those who receive a prophet in the name of a prophet, shall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive a prophets reward,</hi> Matt. 10.41. <hi>This is to make friends of the mammon of unrighteousness, that when ye fall, they may receive you into everlasting habitations,</hi> Luke 16.9. <hi>To pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:95175:5"/> your selves bags which wax not old, a treasure in heaven that faileth not, where no thief approacheth, neither moth cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupteth,</hi> Chap. 12. v. 33. You cannot but think this profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table Usury, if you dare take the Word of God for your Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curity; which that you may the better do, he will give you part of your reward in hand. He hath promised, that <hi>He that giveth to the poor shall not lack,</hi> Prov. 28.27. <hi>Honour the Lord with thy substance, and with the first fruits of thy in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crease; so shall thy barns be filled with plenty, and thy presses shall burst out with new wine,</hi> Prov. 3.9, 10. <hi>There is that scattereth, and yet increaseth,</hi> ch. 11. v. 24. <hi>Cast thy bread upon the waters, for thou shalt find it after many days,</hi> Eccles. 11.1. You shall certainly have these temporal good things, if good for you; And who would desire them on other terms? Or (to compensate the forbearance) <hi>a far more exceeding and eternal weight of glory, reserved in heaven for you.</hi> And I think, that for one single instance of any that have ruin'd themselves (as 'tis falsly call'd) by their real Charity, a thousand might be given of those who have spent all in rio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous living. This will obviate that common Objection, What! would you not have us provide for Age or Sickness? Is it not our duty to take care of our Families? No doubt of it. Yet 'tis as sure, you must not lay up that, which, by the Rules of Justice or Charity, is another's right. Pray con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sider, whether a little with God's Blessing, is not to be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer'd to the largest Estate got or kept by injustice or uncha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritableness. Shall the Word of God determine the contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versy? Psal. 37.16. <hi>A little that a righteous man hath, is bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter than the riches of many wicked.</hi> 'Tis true, even wicked Children should be provided with food and raiment; or at least, put into a condition to do so themselves by their honest labour. But where you have strong probabilities, that what you give them more, will not be well imployed, you ought (if not disinabled by Law, or in some such Case) to bestow it otherwise.</p>
            <p n="4">4. To perswade you to this duty, consider what excellent patterns you have to imitate. God doth good to all, even to the unjust. <hi>Be ye therefore perfect, as your heavenly father is perfect. Consider also the Apostle and High-priest of our pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fession,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:95175:6"/> who became poor that he might make many rich. Who went about doing good</hi> to the Souls and Bodies of men. Which blessed pattern the Primitive Christians did fairly imitate. <hi>Be ye therefore followers of them,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Acts 9 36.10.2.</note>
               <hi>as they were of Christ. Dorcas</hi> was full of good works and alms-deeds which she did. <hi>Cornelius</hi> gave much Alms to the people. St. <hi>Paul</hi> wrought with his own hands, rather than by taking a lawful maintenance, to give the least occasion to his weak hearers, or malicious ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versaries, to say, that he Peach'd for a livelihood. But why do I speak of particular persons? When all that believed were together,<note place="margin">Acts 2.44, 45.</note> and had all things common: And sold their possessions and goods, and parted them to all men as every man had need. And tho the community of goods did not continue long in the Church; yet for some Ages after, their Charity did far exceed ours in these later times.<note place="margin">Dr. <hi>Horneck</hi>'s Letters, p. 492.</note>
               <hi>The Presidents and Pastors of the Primitive Church were known by no other Character but that of Officiousness and Charity; nor had their Shep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herds any other mark to be distinguished by, but their willingness to advance the good of the Sheep, and their readiness unto every good word and work. And indeed, so were the Christians in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral known by their mutual love and kind offices. Those of the highest descent were the forwardest to assist the calamitous in their need; for Religion had mortified in them all punctilio's of Honour and State, and made them remember, that in Christ they were all equal.</hi> The Primitive Christians did so universally obey their Lord's command of loving one another, that the Heathens would usually say,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Fer.</hi> Ap. c. 39. p. 31.</note>
               <hi>See how these Christians love one another!</hi> But their Charity was not confin'd to their fellow-Christians (much less to any one Sect or Party) for they thought no pains or cost too great, that they might convert their very enemies. <hi>Pamphilus bestowed Bibles upon those who were willing to read them.</hi> No small charge in those days, when they had not the conveniency of Printing.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Theod.</hi> Hist. Eccl. l. 5. c. 29.</note>
               <hi>St.</hi> Chrisostom <hi>maintain'd a considerable company of men on purpose to Catechize and instruct the Heathens in the Principles of Christianity.</hi> Neither were they unmindful of mens temporal wants and miseries. <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zianzen</hi> acquaints us,<note place="margin">Orat. 19. p. 298.</note> That <hi>his Father did not only bestow the surplusage of his estate upon the poor, but even part of what he had reserved to supply his own necessities.</hi> And that he had
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:95175:6"/> often heard his Mother say, That <hi>if it were lawful, she could willingly have sold her self and Children, and bestowed the price upon the poor.</hi> One made this short Will: <hi>I will that all my Goods be given to the poor.</hi> But alas! in our days, Ten or Twenty pound, when a Man dieth worth Thousands, is thought enough. Who would think that they and we pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fess the same Religion? Yet there are some (tho but few) amongst us, whose extraordinary Charity may excite us to this duty: A Catalogue of whom you have in Mr. <hi>Gouge</hi>'s <hi>Surest and Safest way of Thriving.</hi>
               <note place="margin">P. 23. ad 31.</note> To which we may add the Reverend Author himself, an account of whose great Charity we have in a Sermon Preach'd at his Funeral by the Reverend Dr. <hi>Tillotson,</hi> too large to transcribe,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gouge</hi>'s Fune<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Sermon. p. 61, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>4, and 85.</note> tho I may have occasion to cite part of it hereafter.</p>
            <p>What now remaineth, but that you speedily practice this great duty to which you are so much obliged in Justice and Gratitude; and encouraged by such excellent Promises and Examples? which if you are resolv'd to do,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>See Baxter</hi>'s direct. how to do good to many; and the Crucif. of the World. Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face.</note> I shall in the se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond place humbly present you with some real objects of Charity, or direct you how to bestow what God shall put in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to your hearts to give.</p>
            <p>Charity respects either the Bodies or the Souls of men. Those whose bodily necessities call for your charity, are ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther such who by reason of Age, Sickness, or the like, are unable to provide for themselves and Families by some ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nest imploy: Or such, who tho they are able to work, yet having either no imployment, or not wherewith to manage their lawful Callings, are no less unable than the former to preserve themselves from begging or starving.</p>
            <p n="1">1. I humbly present you with the former sort, whose pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing necessities call for your speedy relief; imitating herein holy <hi>Job, who delivered the poor that cried; the fatherless, and him that had none to help him.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Job 29.12, 13, 15, 16.</note>
               <hi>The blessing of him that was ready to p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rish</hi> (says that good Man) <hi>came upon me: and I caused the widows heart to sing for joy. I was eyes to the blind, and feet to the lame; I was a father to the poor, and the cause which I knew not, I searched out.</hi> But amongst these, they are first to be relieved who are honest and godly.<note place="margin">Gal. 6.10</note>
               <hi>As we have therefore opportunity, let us do good to all men, especially unto
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:95175:7"/> them who are of the houshold of faith.</hi> And here I cannot but observe the imprudence of too many, who do more fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently relieve idle and wandering Beggers, than honest poor Housekeepers in their own Parish or Neighbourhood; some of whom rather chuse to starve than beg. I do not ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vise you to deny the former, but only put you in mind of the latter, whose modesty permits them not to speak for themselves. I have only this to add, That you would make advantage of this your Charity to the Bodies of Men, for the good of their Souls, by giving them good Instructions, or some good Book suitable to their Condition. This was the Practice of the Reverend Mr.<note place="margin">Funer. Serm. p. 84.</note>
               <hi>Gouge, In this</hi> (i. e. <hi>Pious Charity) he left behind him all that ever I knew; and as I said before, had a singular Sagacity and Prudence in devising the most effectual ways of doing good, and managing his Charity to the best purposes, and to the greatest extent; always, if it were pos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sible, making it serve some end of Piety and Religion; as the instructing poor Children in the Principles of Religion, and fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nishing grown Persons that were ignorant, with the Bible and other good Books. In his occasional Alms to the Poor, in which he was very free and bountiful, the relief he gave them was always min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gled with good Counsel, and as great a tenderness and compassion to their Souls as Bodies.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Others there are who are able to work; and to imploy these is as charitable an Action, as to relieve the former: to which end I shall present you with my L. C. J. <hi>Hales Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>course touching Provision for the Poor;</hi> Wherein you have an account, 1st, of the Provisions already setled by Law. 2d, The Defects in Relation to those Laws or Provisions, and the Consequences thereof. 3. You have a most excellent design to supply those Defects, and remedy those Inconveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences; that is, by erecting Work-houses for the common Use of the respective Parishes, who shall joyn together in so noble and profitable a Design (to themselves, as well as to the poor). See the advantages of such a Design, and all Obje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions answered in the said Book.</p>
            <p>Many poor People might also be imploy'd in the Fishing-trade at Sea. Sir <hi>John Barrow</hi> computeth, that by erecting only 250 <hi>Busses</hi> for the Herring Fishing (which is not a sixth
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:95175:7"/> Part of what the industrious <hi>Hollanders</hi> imploy yearly) either at the publick charge, or by private adventurers thereto au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thorized, there would be found imployment for 20000 Mariners and Fishers at Sea,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heylin</hi>'s Cos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mog. l. 1. p. 254, 255.</note> and as many Tradesmen and Labourers at Land; tho whether this be so practicable as the L. C. J. <hi>Hale</hi>'s design, I leave to the consideration of those <hi>worthy Gentlemen</hi> who study to promote the good of the Publick: To whom I propose this further question, Whether some of our Commons, Heaths, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which are not reserved for his Majesties pleasure of Hunt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and such like uses, and are of little or no advantage either to the Publick, or to private persons; might not be cultivated and improv'd to promote the aforesaid design of building Work-houses? especially if all those, who by Law or Custom claim any priviledg or propriety in them, had reasonable allowances for their said rights and properties: and the Land so improv'd were only or chiefly for the use of the adjacent Parishes.</p>
            <p>And tho my Ld. <hi>Hale</hi>'s design, or others of a like nature, would perhaps be most effectually done by an Act of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, yet in the mean time much might be done by particular persons or Parishes (the Laws now in force favouring it) if men were either charitable to others, or provident for themselves.</p>
            <p>But because great Bodies move slowly, I shall present you with nothing further under this head, but what is in the power of every private person to accomplish: Which is to set poor Boys Apprentices to some honest Trade under a religious Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster. Or to set poor men to work in a private way. Thus did Mr. <hi>Gouge;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ibid. p. 63.</note> where you have not only a worthy pattern to imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate, but the Reverend Doctor's Argument to perswade you to this Duty: And therefore I hope it will not be thought imperti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent (tho large) to transcribe. <hi>As for the other sort of poor who were able to work for their living, he set them to work upon his own charges, buying Flax and Hemp for them to Spin.— And as this was a wise and well chosen way of Charity, and in the good effect of it a much greater Charity, than if he had given those very persons freely, and for nothing, as much as they earn'd by their work; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause by this means he took many off from begging, and thereby re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scued them at once from two of the most dangerous temptations of this World, Idleness and Poverty; and by degrees inclin'd them to a vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous and industrious course of Life, which enabled them afterwards
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:95175:8"/> to live without being beholden to the Charity of others.</hi> If some yearly Rents were given to this purpose, those with whom the Money is intrusted giving security to repay it, the Stock would in time increase to purchase more Land for the same use.</p>
            <p>We come now to the second and more excellent sort of Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, which respects the Souls of Men.</p>
            <p>That you may discharge this part of the Duty of Charity which respects the Souls of Men,</p>
            <p n="1">1. I humbly intreat you to use your utmost endeavours to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the Conversion of the <hi>Jews, Turks</hi> and Heathens, who possess so great a part of the World. It would be a noble work to erect a College to fit men for this work, by learning the Language, Customs, and Religion of the Countries to which they are designed, which would not be so difficult as an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>willing mind may suggest, especially of those Countries where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in Christians have Factories or Plantations. Yea, if it were harder than really it is, Should not zeal to promote the Gospel, make two or three years spent in such studies as pleasant and delightful, as so much spent to acquaint our selves with the opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions and conjectures of Philosophers? And for the Charges (where the greatest difficulty lieth) that would be more or less, according to the number of the men contributing, and imploy'd. And perhaps the service they might do them by being Interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters to Embassadors, would quit the cost of their education and maintenance;<note place="margin">Hist. <hi>Oto.</hi> Em. p. 169.</note> the want whereof Sir <hi>Paul Ricaut</hi> complain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth of.</p>
            <p>Till this be done, I do, with the greatest subm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ssion and ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nestness, intreat Christian Princes, Noblemen, Merchants and others, to imploy some of the Students in the Colleges already erected, in this great design. The only difficulty that remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, is that of access to the Princes and Magistrates of those Countries; which probably might be obtained, if Christian Princes and States would make use of their interest to that end: at least they might be will<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ng to hear what our Religion is, and the Reasons we have for it. O that Christians would study to promote Peace amongst themselves, that they might unani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mously advance the Kingdom of Jesus Christ! The expence of one M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hs War thus imploy'd, would render a Prince truly great and renowned to Posterity. Were I condemn'd to dye by
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:95175:8"/> your just and equal Laws, and now lay at your feet begging for Life, I think I could not do it with more affection and vehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mency than now I do for the miserable uncalled World; whose case would not need an Advocate, might it but be admitted into your Royal thoughts.</p>
            <p>However private men must not neglect their Duty; and much may be done by them, especially Merchants; they might send such Chaplains and Factors into their Factories and Plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations, that would make it their business to promote the Gospel, without neglecting the Affairs of those that send them: They might also get some suitable Books translated into their Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage whose Conversion they endeavour. A cheap way of Preaching!</p>
            <p>'Tis true, the <hi>Turks,</hi> especially those in <hi>Asia minor,</hi> have barbarously put those to death who have attempted to convert one of their Sect to Christianity; holding a kind of an implicit Faith, or that they must not examine the Reasons of their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion. Yet the <hi>Jews</hi> and Heathens (and <hi>Turks</hi> in some places) are not so severe; and perhaps others might easily be convinced of the absurdity of that Opinion, That men ought not to que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stion the Religion they are of. Besides, Sir <hi>Paul Ricaut,</hi> and other late Writers tell us, That the <hi>Turks</hi> of late (especially those called the <hi>Haietti,</hi> and <hi>Chupmessahi,</hi> who maintain that <hi>Christ</hi> is God and Redeemer of the World, the young Scholars in the Grand Signiors Court are generally devoted to this te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent, and great numbers in <hi>Constantinople,</hi> as also the <hi>Eschraki,</hi> whose notions of the Trinity and Paradise (contrary to the vulgar opinion of the <hi>Turks</hi>) much resemble the Christian Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine) are more inclinable to Christianity than formerly. And I know no reason why the <hi>Jews</hi> should be so much neglected by us, as tho we utterly despair'd of their conversion. God hath no where told us that a <hi>Jew</hi> shall not be converted and sav'd; and experience shows us the contrary in these later days: And since they have reasonable Souls, and God hath appointed means equally to be used for the conversion of all men; Why should we neglect to use those means in order to their good? Nay, although they are much prejudiced against the Christian Religion, yet upon some accounts there is more hope of them than others; for they own the same God we worship; and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledg
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:95175:9"/> the <hi>Old Testament</hi> to be his Word; besides, some of them living in <hi>England</hi> and other reformed Churches, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstanding the Languages of those Countries they inhabit, those who by Conference, Preaching, or Writing endeavour their Conversion, need not give themselves the trouble to learn any Language to that end.</p>
            <p>And I think there is more ground for hopes of success amongst the Heathens, than either of the former, they being less prejudiced against Christianity, and having not sin'd against the light of the Gospel; Thousands of them in this Age having not so much as heard of Jesus Christ. The Jesuits have found all this to be true in <hi>China,</hi> if we may give credit to their Letters and Histories, whose industry may justly shame us. Under this Head I shall put you in mind of the Blacks who are Slaves in the <hi>American</hi> Plantations, whose sad condition is represented by Mr. <hi>Goodwin</hi> in a Treatise on this subject.</p>
            <p n="2">2. I humbly present you with your fellow Christians in the Eastern Churches, as another object of your Charity to the Souls of men, who being oppressed by Tyranny and Poverty, and wanting the advantage of Printing to supply them with <hi>Bibles</hi> and other Books, are generally very ignorant; yet not so degenerate in Doctrine or Manners as some represent them. For the first, Mr. <hi>Pagitt,</hi> in his <hi>Christianography,</hi> hath largely prov'd that they agree with us. And for their Manners, I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not imagine what but true Piety should keep many of them so firm to their Religion, under the many temptations by fear of punishment and hope of preferment, wherewith they are dayly assaulted.</p>
            <p>Now my humble request on their behalf is:</p>
            <p n="1">1. That you would furnish them with <hi>Bibles</hi> and other good Books, such as a good Exposition of the <hi>Creed, Lord's Prayer,</hi> and <hi>Commandments,</hi> not medling (especially at first) with their Opinions or Ceremonies wherein they differ from us.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That you would be at the charges to educate some of their youths in our <hi>Universities</hi> till they be fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> for the Ministry, and then send them home; not regarding so much to make them of our mind in lesser matters, as to furnish them (by God's assistance) with that Learning and Piety which may
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:95175:9"/> make them more serviceable in their own Country. Shall not we be at as much pains and charges to promote the knowledg of the Essentials of Religion amongst them, as they of the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> have always been? Especially considering the advantage we may hope to have of them herein? For the <hi>Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cians, Russians,</hi> &amp;c. are so far prejudic'd against the Jesuits, that they suspect their only design is, to advance and enrich them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves by proseliting them to their Party; a famous instance whereof, we have in <hi>A brief discription of the whole World,</hi>
               <note place="margin">P. 59.</note>
               <hi>by the Arch-bishop of</hi> Canterbury; a very pleasant as well as useful story.</p>
            <p>The like hath happen'd in other Countries both Pagan and Christian; but I must forbear to cite them. If then we have greater hopes of success than the Jesuits, Why should we be outdone by them?</p>
            <p n="3">3. I humbly present to your consideration the lamentable and threatning breaches and divisions of the Protestant Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, whereby Love (the character of Christ's Disciples) is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stroy'd, our selves weaken'd, and others prejudiced against our Religion. What Pity is it, that the few and inconsiderable differences amongst us should produce these and many such mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serable effects? Why cannot <hi>Lutherans</hi> and <hi>Calvinists,</hi> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formists and Nonconformists, love as Brethren? Why should we not mourn and rejoyce together, rather than bite and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour one another?</p>
            <p>I pray read the <hi>Protestant Reconciler,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi>'s <hi>True and Only way of Concord,</hi> to this purpose; Books, in my opinion, of great value, whatever Passion or Interest may say to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary.</p>
            <p>'Tis much to be desired, that the Protestant Princes would call a Council out of all Protestant Churches to this end: The want whereof was thought to give the first stop to the progress of the Reformation.</p>
            <p>The foregoing instances of Charity to the Souls of men; chiefly concern Princes, or men of considerable Power and Estates. What I shall further offer, will equally respect all, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept those who stand in need of Char<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ty themselves.</p>
            <p n="4">4. I earnestly entreat you to do your utmost to promote and maintain Religion in your own Families; this all men without
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:95175:10"/> exception may do if they will. In vain do you expect to see Religion prosper in the Church or Kingdom, so long as parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Families are prophane and ungodly. With what face can they speak of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 chunk">
                  <desc>…</desc>
               </gap>ults of their Governors in Church or State, who neglect to Govern their own Families in the fear of God? Is it because thei<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> obligations and advantages are greater than yours? No: But because you can sooner behold the mote that is in your brother's eye, than perceive the beam that is in your own eye.</p>
            <p n="5">5. I desire you (<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> you lieth) to promote a zealous, peaceable and judici<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 chunk">
                  <desc>…</desc>
               </gap> Ministry. How many Souls may be converted by one such? And what way can you think of to lay out your Money to greater advantage? If you have a Son qualified with Wit, Piety, and a zealous desire to serve God in the Ministry; I know not how you can do better, than give him that education which is nec<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ssary to fit him for that sacred Function: If you have none of your own, chuse others so qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lified.</p>
            <p>If you have Presentations, present the best you can procure. And where there are able Ministers, who have not a sufficient maintenance, do them and the people the kindness to aug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment it. <hi>He that receiveth a prophet in the name of a prophet, shall receive a prophets reward.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="6">6. Let me advise you to settle English Schools, where poor Children may be taught to read the <hi>Bible,</hi> and learn their <hi>Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chism;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Funeral Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, p. 89.</note> this is double Charity, to the Body and Soul. Mr. <hi>Gouge</hi> educated every year Eight hundred, sometimes a Thousand poor Children in <hi>Wales.</hi> The meaner sort (those that labour for their own livelihood not excepted) are able to discharge this so great an act of Charity; for in the Countries, where there is most need, you may hire some honest poor Man to teach Children to read the Scriptures, and instruct them in the Principles of Religion, for Ten or Twelve pounds <hi>per Annum;</hi> or if you are not able to do so much, you may pay for the Schooling of as many as you are able. I take this to be the greatest act of Charity the meaner sort are capable of; and I beseech you do not wrong your own and others Souls, by say<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing you are unable, when the truth is you are only unwilling. How miserably do you undervalue Souls, and the price that
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:95175:10"/> was paid to redeem them, when you say you have no Money for these, and yet have enough for less necessary uses? Assure your selves that it is your duty to labour with your own hands,<note place="margin">Eph. 4.28.</note> that you may have wherewith to supply the necessities of others.</p>
            <p>'Tis much to be desired, that Ministers and Schoolmasters would spend more time in Catechizing, and Instructing the ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant in the Principles of Religion. I take this to be as much their duty as Preaching, or Teaching; and am sure that the neglect of it is one great cause of the peoples not profiting by the Sermons they hear. None can deny that this was a consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable part of the publick worship of the <hi>Primitive Christians.</hi> Why then is it so generally neglected in our days? Is it because Preaching is a part of the Ministerial Office, but Catechizing none? Our adversaries I fear will say, 'tis because this is not so fashionable or gainful a part.</p>
            <p>And why sh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uld Schoolmasters neglect it? Is it because they think it more necessary to instruct their Scholars in the Rudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of Grammar and Rhetorick, than in those things that concern their everlasting happiness?</p>
            <p>But if both omit it, methinks Parents should not, whose obligations and advantages are greater than either of the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer. Do you deserve the name of Christians who educate your Children like Heathens? I would have you put your practice into your Creed, and then see how you like it: It would run thus, <q>I believe that my Children and Servants have no Souls to save or lose; or at least, I believe that they may be saved without knowledg, or have knowledg without in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>struction: and therefore I think it more needful to provide them Food and Raiment, and teach them their Trade, than to instruct them in the knowledg of their Creator, Redeemer, and Sanctifier.</q> Why should you abhor this in Opinion, and love it in Practice? I could perhaps (were it needful) offer something that would look like an excuse for Ministers, and neither they nor Schoolmasters can force your Children against your wills: but I can think of no excuse for you; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I desire you, as you love God, your own, or your Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drens Souls, speedily to practice this Duty: Which, that I may perswade you to, I desire you to consider, Deut. 6.7. <hi>And
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:95175:11"/> thou shalt teach them diligently to thy children, and shalt talk of them when thou sittest in thy house, and when thou walkest by the way, and when thou liest down, and when thou risest up.</hi> Eph. 6.4. <hi>But bring them up in the the nurture and admonition of the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="7">7. I desire you to do what you can to promote the practical knowledg of the essential Principles of Religion, by giving Bibles, Catechisms, and plain practical Books to those that will read them, which may be more than you imagine; for I know by experience, that many will highly prize, and dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently read a good Book when given them, that cannot (or are something backward to) buy one: besides they are not so well able to judge which are suitable to their condition. Next to the Holy <hi>Bible</hi> and a good <hi>Catechism,</hi> I conceive these Books to be fit for this purpose; <hi>The Whole Duty of Man. The Practice of Piety.</hi> Dr. <hi>Hammond</hi>'s <hi>Practical Catechism.</hi> Mr. <hi>Gouges</hi> and Mr. <hi>Vincent</hi>'s <hi>Catechism.</hi> Mr. <hi>Allen</hi>'s <hi>Alarm to the Unconverted.</hi> Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi>'s <hi>Call,</hi> and his <hi>Family-Book,</hi> and his <hi>Catechising of Families.</hi> You may soon read these or such like Books over, and then chuse for your selves. If any be offended that I name the Books of Episcopalists and Presbyterians together; I only say, that my present design knows no parties: I only press that wherein all sides are agreed; and having named some Books on both sides, I leave you to your choice, tho I cannot well suppose my Reader so ignorant, as to think there is any differ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence between the Conformists and Nonconformists in their Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrinal or Practical Writings, but only in the Discipline and Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies of the Church.</p>
            <p>I have only this to desire at your hands, That you would pardon the faults of the Author, and assure your selves, That neither they, nor any other pretence whatever, will excuse your neglect of the main design of this Paper.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="publishers_note">
            <p>THe Art of Painting in Oyl. Wherein is included each particular Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumstance relating to that Art and Mystery. Containing the best and most approved Rules for preparing, mixing, and working of Oyl-Colours, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> by <hi>J. S.</hi> C. M. Sold by <hi>Sam. Crouch,</hi> at the Corner of <hi>Popes-head Alley</hi> in <hi>Cornhill.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>